Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival Collection GLTBQ.2013.02
GLBTQ Archives, Central Connecticut State University
Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival Collection
1982 - 2012
GLTBQ.2013.02
GLBTQ Archives, Central Connecticut State University
2.0 Linear feet
The first Hartford, Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival took place on the lawn of Hartford’s Old State House June 26, 1982, from noon to three in the afternoon. Each of the eight organizers invited several friends, hoping that it would help boost the turn out. To their surprise, between 200 and 250 people showed up. By 2011, the festival had grown to accommodate well over 10,000 people. The day-long festival eventually adopted a format that began with a rally, then a march to the festival grounds. For many years, the rally began at the State Capitol, with the festival being held at Bushnell Park. The festivals were political, celebratory, and helped to foster communication between the different groups within the gay community. In addition to political speakers, another component of the early festivals included performances.
Related Archival Materials note
Oral history interviews of Carol Gale, Richard Stillson and Carolyn Gabel-Brett are available within the History 301 Oral History Project (GLTBQ2013.03) Collection of the GLTBQ Archives. Carol Gale's interview, specifically referencing the beginning of the PRIDE festivals, can be accessed within the Digital Collections of the GLTBQ Archives of the Elihu Burritt Library at Central Connecticut State University.
Biographical/Historical note
The first Hartford, Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival took place on the lawn of Hartford’s Old State House June 26, 1982, from noon to three in the afternoon. It was organized by eight members of a group called the Greater Hartford Lesbian and Gay Task Force. No march was planned, but tickets were sold for seats on a bus to the New York’s Christopher Street Liberation Day Parade the next day. Part of the festival included a special showing of lesbian and gay films at Trinity College’s Cinestudio. Each of the eight organizers invited several friends, hoping that it would help boost the turn out. To their surprise, between 200 and 250 people showed up. By 2011, the festival had grown to accommodate well over 10,000 people.
In 1984, in order to separate the activities of organizing the festival from other political activities, the Connecticut Lesbian and Gay Pride Festival (CLGPF) was formed. The previous group eventually grew into the Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian and Gay Civil Rights, now the Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual and Transgender Civil Rights.
The Connecticut PRIDE Committee also worked to produce the festivals. According to the 1997 By Laws of the Connecticut PRIDE Committee, PRIDE stands for: P(eople) R(especting) I(ndividual) D(iversity) E(veryday). Eventually, the name of the organization producing the festival became the Connecticut PRIDE Hartford Rally and Festival, Inc.
The day-long festival itself adopted a format that began with a rally, then a march to the festival grounds. For many years, the rally began at the State Capitol, with the festival being held at Bushnell Park. This changed in 2012, when the organizers decided to cancel the festival due to the increase in cost. Information on the details of this decision is in a letter that was published on the producer’s website. It is now part of the collection.
The festivals were political, celebratory, and helped to foster communication between the different groups within the gay community. In addition to political speakers, another component of the early festivals included performances. One volunteer performance troupe calling themselves the “Signsations” wore a black sash with the name written in silver glitter. As the festival grew in size, commercial interests also grew. Sponsorships and vendors helped to pay for the increase in the costs of the event. Evidence of this can be seen within the realia contained in the collection.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged into four series: Programs and notes, Articles on festivals, Photographs and other graphic materials, and Realia.
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains programs, flyers, articles and realia relating to the festivals over the years, with the bulk of the material dating from 1982 through 2000. In addition, information regarding the LGBT State Employees Association and their fight to win “State Pride” are located in the collection.
Gabel, Carolyn; Gale, Carol; Hartford Gay and Lesbian Health Collective.; Gay community -- Connecticut; Gay liberation movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Gay pride parades; Gay rights -- United States -- History; Gays -- Connecticut -- Exhibitions; Lesbians -- Connecticut -- Exhibitions
- Programs and notes, 1990-2009
  - Gale, Carol -- notes on collection and donation list, December, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lesbian and Gay Pride Festival, June 26, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Unity in the Community, June 25, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Coming Out = Political Clout, June 23, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - You Ain't Seen Nothing Yet, June 29, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Forward Together...There's No Stopping Us Now, June 8, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Don't Hide, June 27, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gay and Great in '88, June 25, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Stonewall 20, A Generation of Pride, June 24, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1990 Connecticut Gay Pride Festival brochure [missing], June 24, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Together in Pride, June 15, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Pride = Power, June 20, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A Family of Pride, June 19, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stonewall 25, June 11, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pride From Silence to Celebration, June 17, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pride Without Borders, June 22, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Equality Through Visibility, June 21, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pride Day Interfaith Prayer Service Hartford, June 20, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Unity Through Diversity, June 20, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - A Proud Past A Powerful Future, June 19, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - People Respecting Individual Diversity Everyday, October 7, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Connecticut PRIDE New Haven, June 9, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Embrace Diversity, September 22, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pride World Wide, September 21, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Connecticut PRIDE New Haven 2002, June 1, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Peace Through Pride, September 13, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Stand Out Proud Together, September 18, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - New Haven Pride Block Party, June 5, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Equal Rights No More, No Less, September 24, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Connecticut PRIDE 2006 --celebrating 25 years of PRIDE in Connecticut, September 9, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Dare To Be Different [photocopies of articles and emails about the 2007 PRIDE rally and festival], June 30, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - My Pride My Soul, Connecticut PRIDE Festival, June 7, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Connecticut PRIDE 2009 [photocopies and emails regarding festival] (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Connecticut PRIDE 2010 [website printout] (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Connecticut PRIDE 2012 "What Happened" [website printout] (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Connecticut PRIDE Insurance Coverage, 1985-1994 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Connecticut PRIDE Program Book Ad Copies with notes and lists of advertisers, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Metroline June 12 1997 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - State PRIDE: The LGBT state Employee Assn, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - State PRIDE: The LGBT State Employee Assn., 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Articles on festivals (Box 1)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festivals 1983 - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1990 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1991 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1992 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1993 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival1994 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1995 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1996 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1997 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1998 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 1999 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE festival 2000 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival 2001 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival 2002 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival 2003 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival 2004 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival 2005 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Articles on Connecticut Lesbian and Gay PRIDE Festival 2006 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Connecticut Gay PRIDE Dance [flyers], undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Urich, William, Articles on Gay Pride, 2006-2008 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- Photographs and other graphic materials, 1982 - 2012 (Box 2)
  - 8th annual Connecticut Gay & Lesbian Film Festival Ad (printer's copy), May 10, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ridgefield pride 2001 photographs (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "Dos Lesbos" performance publicity packet, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs from 1988 and 1989 festivals, 1988, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photos from Connecticut Pride Parade October 7, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Chapin, Cary. Photo negatives and note, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - RitzPak box of photographs from CT Pride, 2001. (Box 2, Object 1)
  - Magnetic car poster “1997 CT P.R.I.D.E. Grand Marshalls Lesley Brett Carolyn Gable" (Box 2, Object 5)
  - Stonewall 25 Connecticut PRIDE Day [eleven posters], June 11, 1994 (Box 2, Object 6a, 6b & 6c)
  - Connecticut Lesbian, Gay & Bisexual Pride Day [poster], Saturday June 19, 1993 (Box 2, Object 7)
  - Photographs of “Members of Imperial Sovereign Court of All Connecticut” [newspaper clipping], June 18, 2003 (Box 2, Object 8)
  - Connecticut PRIDE Guide 2000 [matted cover of program] (Box 2, Object 9)
  - P.R.I.D.E. Fest 1999 [matted cover of program] (Box 2, Object 10)
  - P.R.I.D.E. Fest 1998 [matted cover of program] (Box 2, Object 11)
  - P.R.I.D.E. Fest 1997 [matted cover of program] (Box 2, Object 12)
  - A Family of PRIDE 1993 [matted cover of program] (Box 2, Object 14, Object 13)
  - Pride = Power Connecticut PRIDE Guide 1992 [matted cover of program] (Box 2, Object 15)
  - Stonewall 20 Connecticut PRIDE Guide 1989 [matted cover of program] (Box 2, Object 16)
  - Don't Hide Connecticut PRIDE Guide 1987 [matted cover of program], June 27, 1987 (Box 2, Object 17)
  - Connecticut PRIDE Guide 1986 [matted cover of program] (Box 2, Object 18)
  - Connecticut PRIDE Guide 1984 [matted cover of program], June 23, 1984 (Box 2, Object 19)
  - Flyers, brochures and realia collected in the CLGPF circa 2009 (Box 2, Object 2)
  - PRIDE Button collection (9 buttons mounted on a matte board), 1985-1996 (Box 2, Object 3)
  - PRIDE festival buttons [envelope containing six buttons], undated (Box 2, Object 4)
- Realia
  - Purple linen arm band for 12 anniversary of Stonewall Rebellion, New York City, June 28, 1981 (Box 2, Object 20)
  - Plain purple arm band, June 28, 1981 (Box 2, Object 21)
  - Two homemade blue berets used as a gag, symbolizing the anti-gay Christian Right., undated (Box 2, Object 22a & 22b)
  - Signsations sashes [five black with silver glitter letters', undated (Box 2, Object 23a, b, c, d, e)
  - Giant check written for $1,000, June 27, 1987 (polyester banner) (Box 2, Object 24)
  - “Lesbianism Better Than the Rhythm Method" [Linen Banner with felt letters], undated (Box 2, Object 25)
  - “Lesbian/Gay Pride Festival 1994” [Black silk Jacket ] (Box 2, Object 26)
  - Connecticut PRIDE T Shirts
    - Lesbian and Gay Pride Festival, June 26, 1982 (Box 3)
    - Unity in the Community, June 25, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Coming Out = Political Clout, June 23, 1984 (Box 3)
    - You Ain't Seen Nothing Yet, June 29, 1985 (3) (Box 3)
    - Forward Together...There's No Stopping Us Now, June 8, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Don't Hide, June 27, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Gay and Great in 88, June 25, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Stonewall 20, A generation of Pride, June 24, 1989 (Box 3)
    - Connecticut 10th Annual Pride Festival, June 23, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Pride Without Borders, June 22, 1995, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Equality Through Visibility, June 21, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Equality Through Visibility, Security, June 21, 1997, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Unity Through Diversity, June 20, 1998 (Box 3)
    - 25 years of Pride Connecticut Pride 2006 (Box 3)
    - Pride World Wide Connecticut 2002 (Box 3)
    - Connecticut Pride 1981-2001 (Box 3)
    - Pride = Power Connecticut Lesbian and Gay Pride Day [two white], 1992 (Box 3)
    - Pride = Power Connecticut Lesbian and Gay Pride Day; “Committee Member” on back, 1992 (Box 3)
  - T Shirts worn on PRIDE day
    - Diversity Moves Us Forward, with Fleet Bank logo [two, one purple, one red], 1998 (Box 4)
    - Silence = Death [blue with pink triangle], undated (Box 4)
    - American Standard Gay Pride Coast to Coast, undated (Box 4)
    - Artists Against AIDS, 1994 [white, sleeveless] (Box 4)
    - First In Nation March 21, 1999 Connecticut Coalition for Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender Civil Rights [white, sleeveless] (Bin 4)
  - The 22nd Connecticut Gay and Lesbian Film Festival [Banner], May 22-30, 2009 (Oversize On shelf)